<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Pcwizz&#x27;s blog</title>
        <link>https%3A//pcwizz.net</link>
        <description>Nerd by the name of Pcwizz writes about DevOps, politics, and Free Software.</description>
        <generator>Zola</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <atom:link href="https%3A//pcwizz.net/tags/hardware/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        
            <item>
                <title>Inside the librem 13</title>
                <pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <link>https%3A//pcwizz.net/insidethelibrem13/</link>
                <guid>https%3A//pcwizz.net/insidethelibrem13/</guid>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;disclaiming-bias&quot;&gt;Disclaiming bias&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have already taken the bottom my librem 13, as I like to act like the average
prole, so I can give an initial report on the internal layout and wire runs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest I took the bottom off to upgrade the memory and slot in an ssd, but
I thought it might be some next level autism to write about it. I&#x27;m not really
an expert on PCB design or laptop internal layouts, but I have taken lots of
things apart.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favourite laptop for build quality is in fact my x200, as everything was
covered in a plastic dust&#x2F;splash proof wrap, meaning everything had remained
extremely clean despite it being many years old. I don&#x27;t really expect anything
other than thinkpads to compare to the exceptional attention to detail found in
the x200&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did spend a couple of summers during college&#x2F;high school years churning out
workstations and servers wich is also why I have an unhealthy obsession with
cable ties, cable tension, bend radius and screw types. People very easily
overlook important factors such as cable tension tending towards over taught
cables that are both a pain in the ass to perform maintenance on and degrading
to the cables lifespan. That said I have no formal training in the matter only
habits I have contracted from fellow neckbeards or formulated myself.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;initial-inspection&quot;&gt;Initial inspection&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It looks like pretty much any other modern laptop internal: A compact
motherboard situated in the top left, a respectable battery tacking up the
entirety of the palm rest, a single slot for sdram, a minipcie (populated with
the wifi card), a 2.5&amp;quot; sata drive and an m.2 sata connector to the right. As you
would expect of an i5 their is a fan positioned in the middle exhausting heat
out of a rear vent from a thick copper heat pipe. The rear vent appears to be
unfiltered and run right the way along the back of the case. The heatsink had a
small block of what looks to be thermal transfer foam to utilize the metal
bottom cover; the bottom of the laptop gets warm.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a fair bit of that matt black tape in use to keep wires in place,
mostly around the wifi module. It seems that some of the cable could have been
made a little shorty for tidiness, but it might be better in the long term for
maintenance. The wires for the cmos battery were not afflicted by the tape but
had been looped affectionately round the connector in one elliptical coil; I
dare not touch it for fear that it would never go down again.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The screws attached the board to the case seemed to be small black painted
screws. I didn&#x27;t look around closely for a ground other than the one for the
wifi card which was a wire with the end trapped under a screw, not a screw one
would ever have reason to remove so it&#x27;s fine with me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;populating-the-m-2-sata&quot;&gt;Populating the M.2 sata&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s a standard insert at 45 degrees then lower to horizontal and screw affair.
The only niggle is that they don&#x27;t seem to populate the screw hole if you don&#x27;
order it with a M.2 sata drive; I had to find my own screw.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;changing-the-ram&quot;&gt;Changing the RAM&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They had put some kingston memory in there which is fine; I just wanted more
than I had ordered with the machine. There is only a single dim slot that works
in the way you think it does if you have changed ram in a laptop before. I went
for a 1.35v dim I think that is what was in there I didn&#x27;t check.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Librem 13 first impressions</title>
                <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <link>https%3A//pcwizz.net/librem13firstimpressions/</link>
                <guid>https%3A//pcwizz.net/librem13firstimpressions/</guid>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;packaging&quot;&gt;Packaging&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dull generic but adequate&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;look&quot;&gt;Look&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shiny, clean and nice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;built-quality&quot;&gt;Built quality&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fairly good&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;keyboard&quot;&gt;Keyboard&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not what I&#x27;m used to but not problematic.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a windows key!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t like the shortened right shift key to make room for a function modifier.
Hopefully I cn remap the function modifier to something more useful.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The function keys work as expected.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;kill-switches&quot;&gt;Kill switches&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They aren&#x27;t labelled but there are only two so it&#x27;s not hard to figure out.
Screen&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would be perfect for the size however there is a bit of back light bleed on the
bottom edge. The bleed is not awful and can only be seen on a blacked screen
it&#x27;s not something that I can&#x27;t live with our would typically RMA when buying
for personal use.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;trackpad&quot;&gt;Trackpad&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t like trackpads, this one is very big, they get in the way of me typing;
there is a function key to turn it off. I&#x27;ll get used to it I guess.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;noise&quot;&gt;Noise&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is some noise from the air leaving the vents between the lid an the main
body. it&#x27;s not very loud nor is it distracting; I only noticed it when in the
quietest room in my house. If you have equipped it with a rust platter as I have
then that will be your primary noise creator.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sound-and-speakers&quot;&gt;Sound and speakers&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It works; it plays sound. I&#x27;m a bit of an audiophile I&#x27;m already invested in an
amp&#x2F;dac and a nice pair of headphones so I don&#x27;t really care what is built in.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;wireless&quot;&gt;Wireless&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s an Atheros chip fully supported by the ath9k driver as it stated on the
campain page. Those of us who give a dam know what that means.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;boot&quot;&gt;Boot&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well it didn&#x27;t come with coreboot. I will be installing coreboot myself so I can
have a grub payload required for &#x2F;boot to be encrypted.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;pure-os&quot;&gt;Pure OS&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mine shipped with pure os not Qubes. In fact I believe mine shipped with RC2. I
didn&#x27;t like it it didn&#x27;t seem to have any packages. I installed subgraph rather
quickly after first boot.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
